Mariano Riva Palacio Collection:
University of Texas at Austin
- Enero-Junio 1850
  - 3747 _____. Iguala, January 19, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Approval by Riva Palacio of list of Senators and Deputies; services of Trinidad Gómez, recommended by Riva Palacio, accepted; Luis Medero; transmittal of documents on project for road to Acapulco from Mexico; receipt of portrait of Guerrero, chargeable to the Ayuntamiento de Tixtla.
  - 3748 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, January 19, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Death of sister Mariquita; report of Arista on contract for road to Acapulco.
  - 3749 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, January 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Return of papers for house in San Ángel; Miguel Moza; Flores Alatorre; Hipólito; robbery along roads and loss of tobacco; suspects in Acapilco and Cuajimalpa.
  - 3750 Barajas, Ceferino. Mexico, January 19, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Correspondence with Téllez in Cuernavaca concerning [Rodríguez] papers; arrangements with Cumplido; Mariano; Sabino Flores; request of Dolores Zozaya to watch body of Rodríguez; rapid removal of remains to new tomb under order of the Junta de Salubridad.
  - 3751 [Guerrero de Riva Palacio,] Dolores. Mexico, January 19, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Collection of $50 by Prudencio from Gavilán; horses recovered by Bustamante; Vega; visit to exposition of paintings with Juan Francisco and Javi[e]rcita; Salomé; Julián.
  - 3752 Cruz, Vicente. Cuautitlán, January 19, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Meeting with Pedro María Anaya; collection of toll.
  - 3753 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Yautepec, January 19, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Inspection of Jonacatepec and Morelos; Padre Castillo; reliance on Peña; Hacienda de Casaharo(?); protest against threats of fines.
  - 3754 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, January 19, 1850. LS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Recommendation for Captain Román González for vacancy as Recaudador de las contribuciones in Cuautitlán; service with troops of Cuautitlán in Campaign of La Sierra.
  - 3755 Saviñon(?), D. Mexico, January 19, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 11 × 18 cm.
    Transmittal of claim involving forced loans.
  - 3756 Villar, José del. Mexico, January 20, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Ortega; settlement of accounts; Zumpango.
  - 3757 Herrera, José J. de. Mexico, January 21, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Manuel Flores Alatorre in furtherance of his literary career.
  - 3758 Cruz, Agustín. Tenango, January 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Travel to Tenería; rebel activity in Tenango; Pedro.
  - 3759 Echeverría Mar[tíne] z(?). Mexico, January 22, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of leave of absence via Arista.
  - 3760 Escudero, Agustín. Texcoco, January 22, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Ignacio Chávez for command of the rurales; imprisonment of famous bandit Pedro Beltrán; special privileges allowed him blamed on Bravo, the Prefect, and his gift of weapons to the Prefecture.
  - 3761 [Guerrero de Riva Palacio,] Dolores. Mexico, January 23, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    References to Javierita; Prudencio; Julián; visit by López Monroy(?).
  - 3762 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, January 23, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Crisis reported by Riva Palacio on the 20th; supply of rifles.
  - 3763 Flores Pensado, Ignacio. Mexico, January 23, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 13 × 21 cm.
    Recommendation for Rojas of Ameca attributed to Sabino Flores; Cervantes; secret removal of remains of Rodríguez, assisted by his brother Francisco Rodríguez; complaints before the Junta del Colegio; Río de la Losa; Fonseca; set of Buffon taken by Sánchez Solís; Colegio de Letrán's possession of archives of the State of Mexico from time of the federation; Gondra; removal of the archives by Vicario fijo de Cuajimalpa on leaving the college.
  - 3764 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, January 23, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of urgent message to send an escort to Puebla; concentration of local forces from Ozumba, Tlalmanalco, and Ameca; troops of Oliveros; note from Comandante de Córdoba; guards for Río Frío road.
  - 3765 Escandón, Manuel. Mexico, January 23, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Order for report from Prefecto Juan V. Buchan; dental work; separation of Mineral del Monte and El Chico from Pachuca.
  - 3766 Goya, Juan Bautista. Chalco, January 24, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Unofficial aid given his father-in law Cristóbal Castro as tesorero municipal of Chalco; discharge of Castro by Alcalde Primitivo Martínez on orders of Prefecto Herrera; Juan Blanz; protest against injustice of the act.
  - 3767 Riva Palacio, Mariano. [Borrador de carta a Trinidad Gómez.] Toluca, January 24, 1850., 1 l. 19 × 21 cm.
    Receipt of letter from Álvarez concerning his appointment.
  - 3768 Zamora, J. S[alomé.] Mexico, January 25, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Registration at Colegio de San Ildefonso; reasons for leaving service of Riva Palacio family.
  - 3769 Haro y Tamariz, A. de. Mexico, January 25, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of $3,000 from Riva Palacio for Sánchez Solís, Director of the Institute, as endowment fund; fear of Mariano Arista; Joaquín.
  - 3770 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, January 25, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Arrival in Zacualpam; removal of Alcalde Rafael Romero; appointment of cousin Francisco; election of Síndico and Regidor.
  - 3771 Andrade, Cristóbal. [Carta a José María Verdiguel.] Huejutla, January 25, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Vicente Violante, Subprefecto del Partido de Yahualica, applicant for post as Administrador de Rentas; José Solares, Alcalde, disqualified.
  - 3772 Arista, Mariano. Mexico, January 26, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Urgent request for attendance of Escudero at Chamber of Deputies; message to Cuernavaca.
  - 3773 Bassoco, José María de. Mexico, January 26, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Criticism of political influence of sueldistas; article written on fiscal policy.
  - 3774 León, Esteban V. Tem[]c, January 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Arrangements with Alas for Casa de ensaye; Calderón; pay of fuerza de seguridad dependent on tax on silver in Zacualpam and Sultepec; income from Rentas del Tabaco.
  - 3775 Lezama, Juan. Tulancingo, January 26, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Governor's concern for public education; school taught by brother, recommended by Revilla; funds refused by the Ayuntamiento.
  - 3776 Castera, José María. Mexico, January 26, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for funds for building road to Morelia; payment of toll at Garita de la Sordana avoided by route via Barranca de Santa Anna.
  - 3777 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, January 26, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Arrangements for patrolling road from Santa Fe to Las Cruces; school funds; plan to resign from Senate.
  - 3778 Barrientos, José María. Vicario capitular del Arzobispado de México, January 26, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Effort to influence the Provincial de Santo Domingo in affair at Cua[u]tla; claims of P. Castillo; report of Promotor fiscal at Texcaliacac.
  - 3779 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, January 26, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Opposition of office-holders to legislative economies; encouragement in firm governmental stand; contract for tolls on Cuautitlán road.
  - 3780 Sierra y Rosso, Ignacio. Mexico, January 27, 1850. ALS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead of Dirección General de Aduanas Marítimas, Fronterizas, y Rentas no Estancadas.
    Resignation of Candar as legal representative of Ignacio Moya; Juez Lic. Madrid; Atristain.
  - 3781 Atristain, Miguel. Mexico, January 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Debt due Ignacio Moya at Hacienda de Tetelco; alcabala; delay requested by Sierra y Rosso; care of son of Alarcón; appointment of executor urged.
  - 3782 León, Esteban V. Tem[]c, January 27, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 26 cm.
    Arrangements for son of Major José Guerra to attend the Instituto literario, sponsored by the Municipalidad; request for orders to Zacualpam and Sultepec to pay local troops from tax on silver.
  - 3783 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, January 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plan for patrolling road during fair; Arista; disposition of Pedro Beltrán.
  - 3784 Villaseñor, Alejandro. Cuernavaca, January 27, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Public order in Yautepec; purchase of cannon; watch over affairs in Morelos; Governor's right to levy fines on officers questioned; criticism of Escudero.
  - 3785 Robledo, Manuel T. Mexico, January 27, 1850. LS., 2 l. 13 × 20 cm.
    Recommendation for Pablo García.
  - 3786 [Guerrero de Riva Palacio,] Dolores. Mexico, January 28, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letter delivered by Terreros; Sánchez Solís; Javierita's cough; Prudencio; Salomé; rent on house of Juan Núñez.
  - 3787 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, January 28, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Protest by haciendas in the Tierra Fría against increase in taxes.
  - 3788 Arizcorreta, Mariano. Hacienda de San Bartolomé, January 28, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Recommendation for Presbítero Tomás Miranda; report on meeting held by the Vicario capitular.
  - 3789 Rebollar, Antonio. Texcoco, January 28, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Explanation of treatment of Pedro Beltrán; complaint of prison conditions; medical examination by Dr. Miguel Enciso; agreement of Judge Agustín Vera; lack of charges against Beltrán; notices sent to Puebla, Teotihuacán, and Mexico; settlement of case of Cervantes and Belaunzarán; Tonconita (?).
  - 3790 Flores Pensado, Ignacio. Mexico, January 29, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Controversy over examination of remains of Rodríguez [Puebla]; Francisco; Dolores; Sra. Pedraza; Cervantes; samples of smallpox vaccination serum sent via Sánchez Solís; Barajas; Lozano.
  - 3791 Valderrama, Gabriel. Yautepec, January 29, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Complaints about taxes; order of court for Judge from Tetecala to investigate Ayuntamiento charges against Juez Castillo.
  - 3792 Sánchez Munibe, Joaquín. Fielato de Yautepec, January 29, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Order of Supremo Tribunal de Justicia for the Judge of Tetecala to investigate the local Juez de Letras; charges of the Ayuntamiento against Juez Castillo; local school; road to Morelos.
  - 3793 Cruz, Agustín. Tenería, January 30, 1850. ALS., 3 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Criticism of Riva Palacio in El Progreso; tree plants sent to Toluca; return of Frías; Piedra; Pedro. Includes notes on Guardia Nacional de Tenancingo; escort for prisoners; Indian depredations at San Pablo; Joaquín Millán; Juez de Letras de Tenancingo to propose amnesty for Sargento Romero.
  - 3794 [Guerrero de Riva Palacio,] Dolores. Mexico, January 30, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Health of Javierita; Antonino; prevalence of colds and fevers.
  - 3795 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, January 30, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 22 × 27 cm.
    Articles in El Progreso; plan for reduction of salary of state employees; bandit attack on Rancho de Almaya, near Monte del Desierto and Acapilco; arrest of 19; preparation of charges; activity of Santanistas and related parties; Ortega sent to Zumpango; house at San Ángel.
  - 3796 Godoy, José María. Mexico, January 30, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Need for Escudero in Congress; La Luz; criticism of Bocanegra's policy; developments in Guanajuato; bankruptcy of MacKintosh.
  - 3797 Barrientos, José María. Mexico, January 30, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Report on activities of Padres domínicos at Morelos; plan to remove them; report of Promotor Fiscal; Sánchez Mendívil, fellow student of Villanueva suggested as replacement; concern over reception of new párroco secular; Prefecto Villaseñor; Lic. Peña; Cura Calderón.
  - 3798 Sánchez Solís, Felipe. Instituto Literario, January 30, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of favorable remarks about the Instituto Literario made by Claví and Vilar of the Academia de San Carlos, printed in El Siglo.
  - 3799 Ruiz, José Antonio. Mexico, January 30, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Petition of Ayuntamiento de Huasca for reinstatement of Law of January 12, 1833, allowing tax on liquor to support primary school teacher; progressive work of Borbollas.
  - 3800 VECINOS DE ATITALAQUIA. Atitalaquia, January 30, 1850. No signatures., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Petition for removal of Nicolás Cosío, who was arrested for robbery at Tepeji del Río but set free, now instructing the fuerza de gendarmería at Tula.
  - 3801 Colín, José Nicolás E. de. Asunción, January 30, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Care of the crops; wheat at San Bartolo; work of stonemasons; stone fence; road to Temamatla; payroll money brought from El Moral; accounts of Garrido; Luis; Cadena.
  - 3802 Sierra, Manuel María de la. Chalco, January 30, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Report on three men shot by Oliveros; charge of incest; pillage by soldiers.
  - 3803 Rincón, Manuel. Mexico, January 31, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Transmittal of plans for the Cases consistoriales.
  - 3804 Villaurrutia, Antero de. Mexico, January 31, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Settlement of land ownership between Lic. Guerra and Baz and the town of Acuautla; study by Juez de Letras Lic. Sierra and Benito León Acosta; demonstration by Indians; withdrawal of judge to Chalco; request for armed aid from Texcoco.
  - 3805 Andrade, Cristóbal. Huejutla, January 31, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Resignation of Alcalde José Solares of post as Administrador de contribuciones de Yahualica; recommendation for Vicente Violante; request for pay by the Administración de Zacualtipán.
  - 3806 Iturbe, Francisco. Mexico, February 1, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Program for road-building; complaints of hacendados against increase in tax; office-holders' requests for pay; firm policy advised.
  - 3807 Noriega, A. Tlalnep[]a, February 1, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Plan for settling unrest in Cuautitlán; removal of Subprefecto and major in the Guardia nacional; return from Tlalpam; security of Santa Fe; Joaquín.
  - 3808 Cumplido, Ignacio. Mexico, February 1, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm., 1 l. 15 × 21 cm.
    Acceptance of two students from the Instituto to study lithographic processes in the printing house; plan for government use; sale of lithographic press to State of Jalisco; plan for publications in El Siglo; plans for the Rodríguez album. Includes draft of letter of January 29, to which this in an answer; plan to purchase a press for state use; request for instruction for two Institute students.
  - 3809 Castera, José María. Mexico, February 2, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Discussion with Arizcorreta concerning contrata de parque.
  - 3810 Quijano, Benito. Correspondencia particular del Comandante General del Distrito y Estado de Méjico, Mexico, February 2, 1850. LS. 2 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Trial of Lieutenant Colonel Joaquín Villegas; papers sent to Comandante gral. de esa demarcacion D. Mar[ia]no Mart[ín]ez; justification to Arista; consejo de guerra. Seal: MBQ.
  - 3811 Mier y Terán, Gregorio de. Mexico, February 2, 1850. LS., 2 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Letter delivered by Vice-gobernador Luis Madrid; agreement to contribute to fund for jails; poor business conditions; fear of epidemic.
  - 3812 Álvarez, Juan. Iguala, February 2, 1850. LS. 1 l. 21 × 27 cm. Printed letterhead.
    Receipt of advice on road contract; gift of portrait of Vicente Guerrero presented to the Legislature; appointment of Gavilán to Tetecala not recommended; appointment of Álvarez as Gobernador interino by Legislature; Larreátegui to report on Riva Palacio's herds at Jaltianguis; aid to Trinidad Gómez; Cantú.
  - 3813 Malo, José R. Mexico, February 2, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request of Deputy Escudero for Malo to take over the Luz (Mine) litigation from Bocanegra; involvement of MacKintosh as investment; Tribunales de Guanajuato; efforts to re-organize the Hacienda del Estado; unnecessary employees.
  - 3814 Zamora, Blas. Coatepec, February 3, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Protest against writings in El Progreso; Riva Palacio's instructions about freedom of publication; report on Texcoco; illness of Tonchi and writer's mother; brother Pepe; Rebollar.
  - 3815 Pérez Palacios, Ángel. Cuernavaca, February 3, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm., 3 l. 21 × 31 cm.
    Policy on road construction toward Acapulco; side roads to Tenango, Miacatlán, and Tianguistengo and Huitzilac; request for convoy of rurales to escort Lieutenant Joaquín Telles to Mexico to bring artillery piece and supplies; death of sister Mariq[ui]ta. Includes draft of answer, February 8, 1850, approving convoy to Tacubaya; problem of paying damages for losses incurred during American occupation; inadequacy of the Administración de rentas; criticism of tax system operated by Juntas; budget estimates by Rivero; proposal to let out contracts for collection of taxes not favorably considered by members of the Legislature; Don Aparicio; opposition of Zedillo; proposal of the Comisión de Visita; request for co-operation; Don Francisco.
  - 3816 Lebrija, Joaquín. Mexico, February 3, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for letter of recommendation to deputies in the Comisión inspectora: López Portillo, Lic. Hierro Maldonado, Díaz Guzmán, Villaseñor, and Joaquín Navarro.
  - 3817 Escandón, M[anue] l. Mexico, February 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Rumors of difficulties in the house of M[anning?] and M[acKintosh?]; letter to Terán; warning of opposition from employees in efforts to re-organize economic structure of the state government; $1,000 promised for work on the jail; $14,000 loan to market in Toluca; percentage of silver assay at Pachuca and Mineral del Monte; mines of Chico and Pachuca; need for other Ajiotistas like himself; Mineral del Monte and el Chico confused in orders from the Prefecto de Tulancingo; fort at Mineral del Monte.
  - 3818 Escudero, P[edro]. Mexico, February 4, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Malo urged to undertake the Luz litigation; appeal to the Legislature by Atristain; Goribar's discussions with Rovalo over tax collection at Cuernavaca; Toluca; possible bankruptcy of MacKintosh; Romero; Aguirre.
  - 3819 Cervantes, José J. Atenco, February 5, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Pursuit of robber band; Aguirre; Antonio; Ana Bernarda; request for aid to Luisa Josefa Vergara of Las Salinas, whose only son was taken in the leva at Tejupilco; certificate from Temascaltepec.
  - 3820 [Mier y Terán,] Gregorio. Mexico, February 6, 1850. LS., 2 l. 22 × 28 cm.
    Rumors of his financial ruin denied.
  - 3821 Otero, M. Mexico, February 6, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Otero and Flores robbed during return from Puebla; robbers identified as residents of Ameca; discussion with Pedro Escudero over opposition to Riva Palacio's policy of retrenchment; similar opposition by government employees in the capital; weakness of Conservatives in Congress; efforts of MacKintosh to avoid bankruptcy; sale of bonds in Tabaco, Mineral del Monte, and the Casa de Moneda; payments requested of the Congress; Casa de Moneda de Guadalupe, Calvo, and Culiacán.
  - 3822 Villar, José del. Coyoacán, February 6, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Opposition to Mozo's proposal concerning house of Hipólitas; Ayuntamiento; litigation over ownership; agreement with Noriega for building house; charges of murder against prisoners from Acapulco; crimes committed in Monte del desierto; D. Antonio.
  - 3823 Robredo, Teófilo. February 6, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Thanks for influence favoring issue of licenses by the Prefectura.
  - 3824 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, February 7, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Organization of new municipalidades; difficulties caused by the fair; organization of security forces; Vera; Córdoba in charge of Sargento Lara; Oliveros; protection of stagecoaches; Blancs; Reglamento de Gendarmería; arduous service at Río Frío; criticism of Escudero; Captain González; relaxation of law against “diversiones de gallos y toros” requested by Morales; laws against gambling; request for operational funds.
  - 3825 M[artíne] z de Castro, Ramón. February 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Delay in payment of sum promised toward building of new market in Toluca; Ángel Sobrino; illness in family.
  - 3826 Calderón, Lorenzo. Sultepec, February 8, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Departure for Temascaltepec; criticism of articles in El Progreso; recruiting; conduct of the Ayuntamiento; bandit attack on wife of José M. Camposano; León.
  - 3827 Aragón, Antonio. Hacienda de la Compañía, February 8, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for intervention to help brother José María Cedillo, condemned by Oliveros to be shot.
  - 3828 Vivanco, A. [Carta a Vicente Zamora.] Mexico, February 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Request for intervention to protect José María Cedillo from persecution by the Jefe de Policía; profession of arriero on road to Veracruz.
  - 3829 Robles, Manuel. Veracruz, February 9, 1850. LS., 2 l. 20 × 25 cm.
    Recommendation for George A. Clark in efforts to establish communication between Veracruz and Acapulco. Includes note:
    - a. George A. Clark: [Carta.] Mexico, March 12, 1850. 1 l. f. 2. Efforts to establish a line of communication between New Orleans and San Francisco via Veracruz and Acapulco. Embossed design: PPS.
  - 3830 Peña, J. de la. Hacienda del Hospital, February 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Receipt of rifles for the Guardia nacional; approval of new Ayuntamiento; construction of the jail and market; Padre Castillo to be charged by the Vicario foráneo.
  - 3831 Sierra, Manuel María de la. Chalco, February 9, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Co-operation of Oliveros; bandits hanged by Ruiz, Comandante in Ameca; Olivero's effort to apply la ley fuga to Rojas; report of Antonio Herrera; result of trial of a bandit awaited; transmittal of trial of Vargas of Ixtapaluca, delay in trial of Blancs; trial in Juchi over death of Chaves; Gabino.
  - 3832 Villanueva, Zenón. [Carta a Agustín Díaz.] Tecamac, February 10, 1850. LS., 1 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Distribution of cards; feligresía vacated by José María Castillo.
  - 3833 Goribar, J. de. Casasano, February 10, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Contribution of $200 by son Faustino; plan for building roads; Escandón; Pérez Palacios; Rovalo in Santa Inés.
  - 3834 Herrera y Campos, Francisco. Texcoco, February 10, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Reports delivered by Rosell; reports on Blancs awaited from Elías; capture of José Rojas of Ameca by Oliveros; charge against Perdigón; intervention of Sierra; Chávez' clothes sent to Alcalde de Juchi by Oliveros; transfer to Juez de Chalco.
  - 3835 _____. Texcoco, February 11, 1850. ALS., 1 l. 15 × 21 cm.
    Transmittal of report by Oliveros on arrest of José Rojas; Chávez; Rosell.
  - 3836 Tixera, Mateo de la. Mexico, February 11, 1850. ALS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Letter of recommendation for José María Cedillo, wanted by Oliveros as member of a band of Guerrilleros; residence in the Hacienda de la Compañía; service in recent war; unauthorized seizure of coach at San Agustín de la Cueva and delivery to General Álvarez in Tepespa (Tepepa?) and to Pablo Granados during American occupation; work as arriero; Antonio Vivanco; Vicente Zamora; criticism of Oliveros; Juan Bueno.
  - 3837 Escudero, P[edro]. Mexico, February 11, 1850. LS., 2 l. 21 × 27 cm.
    Suggestion of means to end long enmity between Hacienda de los Pozos and the neighboring Indian village; construction of road provided in will of Señora Cortina; mediation between Tapia and Omaña, chiefs of Indians at Mixquiahuala; Atristain.